<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="teibp.xsl"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Paris</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p part="N">HOLD FOR INFORMATION ABOUT THIS PUBLICATION</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <p part="N">HOLD FOR INFORMATION ABOUT THE SOURCE</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <tagsDecl>
                
                <rendition xml:id="italic" scheme="css">
                    font-style:italic;
                </rendition>
                
                <rendition xml:id="small-caps" scheme="css">
                    font-variant:small-caps;
                </rendition>
                
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English</language><!--XML:Do I need this?-->
                <language ident="fr">French</language>
                <language ident="latn">Latin</language>
                <language ident="gr">Greek</language>
                <language ident="ru">Russian</language>
                <language ident="it">Italian</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <note xml:id="briggs.1" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.0.8, l.0.11)">
                Dedication: "To our lady of Paris in recognition of graces granted." "Our Lady of Paris," both the Virgin Mary
                and the <seg xml:id="briggs.1.1">cathedral</seg> dedicated to her on the Ile-de-la-Cite, at the center of Paris, with an echo of the prayer
                "Ave Maria, gratia piena" ("Hail Mary, full of grace"——see line 445). The frame suggests that of a votive plaque
                such as might be hung in a church. From the outset, Paris is addressed as a woman.
                </note>
                <note n="1." xml:id="briggs.2" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.1">
                    "holophrase," a single word standing for a phrase, sentence, or complex of ideas, and according to Jane Harrison (JH)
                    characteristic of an early stage of language development (473-75). "I want" can also mean "I lack." Holophrase puns on "hollow phrase."
                </note>
                <note n="2." xml:id="briggs.3" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.2">
                    <seg xml:id="briggs.3.1">Metro line</seg> from Montparnasse to Montmartre, now line 12 (N[ote]P1).
                </note>
                <note n="3-6." xml:id="briggs.4" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.3, l.6)">
                    Brand names on metro posters (NP1): "<seg xml:id="briggs.4.1">Zig-Zag</seg>," type of cigarette paper advertised with the head of a "zouave,"
                    an Algerian soldier (and anticipating the poem's zig-zag direction through the city); "<seg xml:id="briggs.4.2">Lion Noir</seg>" (black lion), a brand of shoe polish;
                    "<seg xml:id="briggs.4.3">Cacao Blooker</seg>," Dutch make of drinking chocolate. These introduce themes of empire and of <hi rendition="#italic">négritude</hi> (blackness),
                    further linked with "Black-figured vases" (550-480 B.C.), found in Etruscan burial chambers.
                </note>
                <note n="7-9." xml:id="briggs.5" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.7, l.9)">
                    "Rue du Bac," "Solférino" and "Chambre des Députés" (no "Assemblée Nationale"), the three most northerly stations on the
                    Nord-Sud line south of the river (rue du Bac is next to rue de Beaune, where HM lived while writing the poem) "Solférino," 
                    named for a French victoria over Austria in Italy (1859). From 1832, the Chambre des Députés was the Frenhc lower house of government.
                    "Dubonnet," brand of fortified wine advertised in metro tunnels, HM's curved brackets suggesting the walls of the metro on which the posters appeared.
                </note>
                <note n="10." xml:id="briggs.6" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.10">
                    "Brekekekek coax coax," chorus of Aristophanes' <hi rendition="#italic">The Frogs</hi> (405 B.C.) in the underworld (also suggesting rattling
                    wooden carriages in the metro). "Frogs," British slang for the French, used in letters between HM and JH.
                </note>
                <note n="12-13." xml:id="briggs.7" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.12, l.13)">
                    "The Scarlet Woman" appears to St. John on the Greek island of Patmos (<hi rendition="#italic">Revelation</hi> 17.3-6). "Byrrh," another fortified
                    wine, advertised with a poster of a woman dressed in scarlet, playing a drum and shouting (see Cocteau 49, 38 for "BYRRH" and St. John as witness).
                    ["St" before "John" inserted by Woolf on 160 copies.]
                </note>
                <note n="14." xml:id="briggs.8" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.14">
                    "Are you you getting off here, madame?" standard polite phrase for making one's own way off a crowded metro car or bus.
                </note>
                <note n="15-16." xml:id="briggs.9" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.15, l.16)">
                    "Those who weigh themselves [up] often, know themselves well. Those who know themselves well, stay healthy," motto on station scales.
                </note>
                <note n="17." xml:id="briggs.10" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.17">
                    The speaker alights at the first station north of the river, Place de la Concorde, a huge square on the Right Bank, formerly used for royal events,
                    the guillotine during the revolution, etc. Concorde means "agreement," introducing the theme of the peace process (MacMillan, passim).
                </note>
                <note n="20-22." xml:id="briggs.11" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.20, l.22)">
                    The spaced-out layout of these lines imitates that of the Tuileries gardens, with gaps left for the basins on the central axis at either end. 
                    The poems slows down, changing from south > north (vertical movement on the page) to west > east (horizontal). 
                </note>
                <note n="23-26." xml:id="briggs.12" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.23, l.26)">
                    Little boys riding on a carousel in the Tuileries (out of use during WWI) become soldiers, their hands sticky from the mud of the trenches
                    (anticipates lines 89-92, 275-76).
                </note>
                <note n="27-29." xml:id="briggs.13" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.27, l.29)">
                    The pigeons appear to be joined to the statues in the Tuileries, while the statues look "two-dimensional" (273, 403). One, looking over her
                    shoulder, suggests Watteau's "Le Départ pour Cythère" (properly, "L'Embarcation pour Cythère," 1717, in the Louvre), in which those leaving for
                    Cytherea (the island of Venus) look back.
                </note>
                <note n="30-34." xml:id="briggs.14" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.30, l.34)">
                    Some statues are of nymphs. Louis Pasteur (1822-95) developed a vaccine against rabies (Sacha Guitry's play, <hi rendition="#italic">Pasteur</hi>,
                    was running in Paris in early 1919. A metro station on the Nord-Sud line had been named after him). "Gauls," the French, as warriors or soldiers.
                    The Nymphs' soft mouths also suggest female genitals ("nymphae," labia minora); their "bite" may refer to venereal disease.
                </note>
                <note n="34-39." xml:id="briggs.15" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.34, l.39)">
                    Leon Gambetta, national hero and Minister for War during the German siege of Paris, announced the Third Republic in September 1870 (in the
                    presence of the 1919 Prime Minister Georges Clemençeau——the first buried reference to him). Gambetta's statue in a frock coat (now in the square
                    Edouar-Vaillant, 20éme) then stood at the base of a seventy-five-foot monumental pyramid in front of the Louvre, with the winged "Genius of France"
                    leaning over him. HM imagines a red stud (his <hi rendition="#italic">legion d'honneur</hi> rosette) in a button-hole (<hi rendition="#italic">boutonnière</hi>
                    is slang for anus), suggesting a possible sexual intimacy between these two figures.
                </note>
                <note n="36." xml:id="briggs.16" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.36">
                    <hi rendition="#italic">tutoiement</hi>, an intimate form of address (tu), employed by couples.
                </note>
                <note n="37." xml:id="briggs.17" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.37">
                    "But it makes sense."
                </note>
                <note n="38." xml:id="briggs.18" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.38">
                    Esprit Français, "Spirit of France." The winged "Genius" on the Gambetta monument.
                </note>
                <note n="40-42." xml:id="briggs.19" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.40, l.42)">
                    "Secrets," defined by four terms set in a square that play between English and French senses: "exquisite" (Fr. <hi rendition="#italic">exquis</hi>);
                    "significant" (Fr. <hi rendition="#italic">significatif</hi>); "fade," a verb in English, an adjective in French meaning tasteless or insipid; "plastic"
                    (<hi rendition="#italic">plastique</hi>), malleable, molded, flowing, often applied to sculpture or the visual arts, a favorite word for HM (see lines
                    112, 289; <hi rendition="#italic">Madeleine</hi>, vii).
                </note>
                <note n="43-50." xml:id="briggs.20" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.43, l.50)"><!--check-->
                    (Exquisite / significant secrets) Of . . . Goya's painting of the Duchess of Alba (1795, near the end of the war between France, Germany, and Spain)
                    depicts her as tall and slender, a pyramid, resembling both the Eiffel Tower and Gambetta's monument. Red ribbons in her hair and on her dress echo his red
                    stud. She seems drugged, and, like him, is pointing, in her case to a small (Maltese) dog at her feet, as if directing the Magi to the infant Jesus at
                    Epiphany. HM and JH may have seem this painting in Madrid in 1916; Goya was fashionable with the French avant-garde.
                </note>
                <note n="51." xml:id="briggs.21" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.51">
                    (Significant / plastic secrets) Of . . . On the top of the Gambetta monument was a figure of Democracy riding on a lion. <hi rendition="#italic">Lysistrata</hi>,
                    heroine of a play by Aristophanes (411 B.C.), persuaded the women of Athens to end the war with Sparta by going on sexual strike. The play was on at the Marigny
                    Theatre, and another play inspired by it, <hi rendition="#italic">La grève des femmes</hi>, was also running in Paris in spring 1919.
                </note>
                <note n="54." xml:id="briggs.22" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.54">
                    ("Fade" or fading secrets) Of... 
                </note>
                <note n="55-56." xml:id="briggs.23" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.55, l.56)">
                    From the Place du Carrousel, the Arc de Triomphe is visible at the far end of the Champs Elysées. Caesar (whose statue stands in the Tuileries) scorns
                    dreams in Shakespeare's play.
                </note>
                <note n="58." xml:id="briggs.24" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.58">
                    Salle Caillebotte, room in the Musée du Luxembourg, hung with French impressionist paintings. The painter Gustave Caillebotte's unique collection of these
                    was at first refused by the French Government, but from 1896 most of them were on display.
                </note>
                <note n="59." xml:id="briggs.25" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.59">
                    The journey through Paris continues.
                </note>
                <note n="60-61." xml:id="briggs.26" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.60, l.61)">
                    "The Etoile," the <hi rendition="#italic">place</hi> at the top of the Champs Elysées, at the center of the fashionable west side, named "etoile"
                    (star) because twelve avenues radiated from it. "The Bois," (Bois de Boulogne), public park at its western edge.
                </note>
                <note n="62." xml:id="briggs.27" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.62">
                    In J-K. Huysman's decadent novel <hi rendition="#italic">A Rebours</hi> (1884), Des Esseintes has the shell of a living tortoise encrusted with jewels.
                </note>
                <note n="63." xml:id="briggs.28" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.63">
                    "Spinario," Roman statue in bronze (first century B.C.) in the Museo dei Conservatori in Rome. Renaissance copies abound, some in the Louvre.
                </note>
                <note n= "64-65." xml:id="briggs.29" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.64, l.65)">
                    Juliette Récamier, famous beauty and lover of the poet Chateaubriand (362). "Discalceated," rare word for "barefooted," as she appears in a portrait
                    (1800) by Jacques-Louis David (291), in the Louvre. "<hi rendition="#italic">De nos jours</hi>," of our time.
                </note>
                <note n="67-68." xml:id="briggs.30" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.67, l.68)">
                    "Saunters" suggests the  <hi rendition="#italic">flâneur</hi>, stroller or wanderer, a characteristic Parisian type; "rue Saint-Honoré," old street
                    meandering from east to west parallel with the river (Chateaubriand lived at no. 374). "Grand Seigneur," great lord. Brittany, the westernmost region of France,
                    introduces a tour of the provinces.
                </note>
                <note n="70." xml:id="briggs.31" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.70">
                    Auvergnat, hot chestnut-seller, native to the Auvergne, the mountainous area of central France. Celtic Brittany and the Gallic Auvergne represent old
                    traditional French stock. Many nineteenth-century Parisians came from Brittany and central France (Higonnet 77).
                </note>
                <note n="72-77." xml:id="briggs.32" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.72, l.77)">
                    Paris was often pictured as a city of peasants, and its <hi rendition="#italic">quartiers</hi> thought of as villages, especially by the surrealists
                    (see Louis Aragon, <hi rendition="#italic">Le Paysan de Paris</hi> (1926). Many Paris houses have large gates, providing glimpses of "Hidden courts" 
                    decorated with classical figures such as "putti," though the "Little gods" could be the city's artists, musicians and writers.
                </note>
                <note n="78." xml:id="briggs.33" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.78">
                    The Gallic cock is a national symbol. The cock wakens the farmer, usually banishing ghosts, though here it becomes the ghost of Hesiod, an early Greek
                    poet who "sang" (as the cock does) of country life in his <hi rendition="#italic">Works and Days</hi> (both denied to the dead). "Acheron," one of four
                    rivers of the classical underworld/afterlife.
                </note>
                <note n="84." xml:id="briggs.34" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.84">
                    That is, peace; also the "Eniautos Daimon," whose birth and death correspond to seasonal change, the central theme of JH's <hi rendition="#italic">Themis</hi>.
                </note>
                <note n="86-88." xml:id="briggs.35" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.86, l.88)">
                    The Spirit of the Year is laid out, corpse-like, in fields whose ploughed furrows ("nos sillons") suggest the fluted drapery of archaic Greek statues,
                    as well as the trenches of WWI.
                </note>
                <note n="90-93." xml:id="briggs.36" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.90, l.93)">
                    Children hung with amulets (good luck charms, to protect from danger) are also reincarnated soldiers (as at line 23; see Cocteau 41).
                    "<hi rendition="#italic">Pigeon vole</hi>" (literally, "pigeon, fly"), children's game that also recalls extensive use of pigeons to carry military
                    information in WWI. Red and blue are the colors of Paris, and the blue smocks recall the blue uniforms of French soldiers (as at line 275).
                </note>
                <note n="95-99." xml:id="briggs.37" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.95, l.99)">
                    "At Bon Marche, Spring Outfits Available Now." Bon Marche, large department store in the rue de Babylone, subject of Zola's 1883 novel,
                    <hi rendition="#italic">Au Bonheur des Dames (Ladies' Paradise)</hi> (Higonnet 200). 
                </note>
                <note n="100." xml:id="briggs.38" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.100">
                    "jeunesse dorée," gilded youth, used of wealthy, spoilt young people, but also of the buds on the sycamore trees. 
                </note>
                <note n="101-2." xml:id="briggs.39" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.101, l.102)">
                    Mauve or purple is the ritual color used in Lent. 
                </note>
                <note n="104-5." xml:id="briggs.40" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.104, l.105)">
                    "Crocuses, / Chionodoxa," flowers of early spring. Crocuses are usually mauve. Blue or white, Chionodoxa, meaning "glory of the snow," a 
                    suitable name for a fairy-tale princess. Serbia also recalls the assassination of the Archduke at Sarajevo that triggered WWI.
                </note>
                <note n="107-8." xml:id="briggs.41" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.107, l.108)">
                    "chef d'oeuvre," masterpiece. The floral pageant runs from crocuses, to lily of the valley sold on May 1 (see lines 235-59; NP13) to the
                    dog-roses of early summer. The dog-roses reverse the gaze of the painters (lines 21-22) by watching the annual pilgrimage of gypsies to
                    Saintes-Marie-de-la-Mer in the Camargue on May 23-25; "wanes," an unusual spelling of "wains," or wagons. "Charles's wain," another name for
                    the Great Bear (see lines 445-46).
                </note>
                <note n="111-14." xml:id="briggs.42" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.111, l.114)">
                    "Roses from Lyons," major city; south-east of Paris. Unlike dog-roses, they are "scentless" (<hi rendition="#italic">fade?</hi>), yet "plastic,"
                    or moulded. In 1913 Joseph Pernet-Ducher named a hybrid tea-rose "Mme Edouard Herriot" after the wife of the then mayor of Lyons.
                </note>
                <note n="115-16." xml:id="briggs.43" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.115, l.116)">
                    French painter J.A.D. Ingres (1780-1867) apparently did not paint Mme Nélie Jacquemart-Andre (1841-1912), herself a portrait painter and
                    art collector. Her home became the Musée Jacquemart-André at 158, Blvd. Haussmann.
                </note>
                <note n="117-21." xml:id="briggs.44" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.117, l.121)">
                    In February 1919, paintings stored underground for safety were re-hung in the Louvre, including the fifteenth-century "Pietà" from 
                    Villeneuve-les-Avignon; Edouard Manet's controlversial nude, "Olympia" (1863), first displayed in 1907 after a campaign by Georges Clemençeau (on Manet,
                    see line 290); "Gil[l]es," Watteau's painting of Pierrot (1718-19); "Mantegna's Seven Deadly Sins," properly "Minerva chasing the Vices from the Garden
                    of Virtue" (ca. 1502); J.-B.-S Chardin (1699-1779) specialized in domestic scenes and still life. 
                </note>
                <note n="123-25." xml:id="briggs.45" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.123, l.125)">
                    "Unetiolated," not pale from being stored in a dark, underground place. Shakespeare's Macbeth claims of his murdered victim, "Duncan is in his
                    grave. / After life's fitful fever, he sleeps well" (III.ii. 22-23). the paintings implicitly contrast with dead soldiers, who cannot be resurrected,
                    and may not "sleep well."
                </note>
                <note n="126-28." xml:id="briggs.46" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.126, l.128)">
                    Greeted rapturously as "Wilson le Juste" on arrival in Paris for the peace talks, U.S. President Woodrow Wilson brought his fourteen-point plan,
                    which promised more than it could deliver (MacMillan 3-20). "Gargantua," figuring old Europe, was an anarchic giant, and title character of Rabelais'
                    fantasy (1534-35); his urine was indeed "diluvial," or flood-like (the French describe heavy rain as "pluie diluvienne"). Wilson's "innocent enjoyment"
                    appeared to Clemençeau "pathetic naiveté" (MacMillan 23). 
                </note>
                <note n="129." xml:id="briggs.47" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.129">
                    "chrysalids," cocoons or pupae that will relase butterflies (as the buds release leaves).
                </note>
                <note n="132." xml:id="briggs.48" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.132">
                    Easter (Good Friday, April 18, in 1919). "Grand Guignol" ("blood and guts") was a violent, sensational type of melodrama performed at the Grand
                    Guignol theatre in Montmartre (see lines 181-82). [HM cut lines 1-5 of this page when the poem was reprinted in 1973.]
                </note>
                <note n="134." xml:id="briggs.49" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.134">
                    Ritual self-flagellation was a regular feature of Good Friday processions.
                </note>
                <note n="136." xml:id="briggs.50" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.136">
                    Little Jesus does a pee-pee. "Le petit jésus," pretty child, can also be slang for a boy prostitute.
                </note>
                <note n="137." xml:id="briggs.51" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.137">
                    Lilac flowers near the end of Lent, its color echoing that of the church draperies (101, 155). 
                </note>
                <note n="138-40." xml:id="briggs.52" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.138, l.140)"><!--check-->
                    <hi rendition="#italic">Song of Solomon</hi> 8.8: "We have a little sister, and she has no breasts" (see also <hi rendition="#italic">Song of Solomon</hi>
                    2:11-12 for its evocation of spring).
                </note>
                <note n="140-42." xml:id="briggs.53" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.140, l.142)">
                    "Quality milk from the Rambouillet farm," the first of a series of street signs. Rambouillet, a small town south-west of Paris, 
                    where Louis XVI created the Ferme de Rambouillet, the Queen's dairy, for Marie Antoinette. The Hótel Ramboullet (in Paris) was the first 
                    and greatest French <hi rendition="#italic">salon</hi> (see <hi rendition="#italic">Madeleine</hi>, ch. IX).
                </note>
                <note n="143-44." xml:id="briggs.54" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.143, l.144)">
                    "The telephone directory can be consulted here."
                </note>
                <note n="145-46." xml:id="briggs.55" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.145, l.146)">
                    "Delicatessen, for best quality cold cuts."
                </note>
                <note n="147-48." xml:id="briggs.56" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.147, l.148)">
                    "Pre-meal drinks" / "Food for diabetics" (literally, "diabetic food").
                </note>
                <note n="149." xml:id="briggs.57" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.149">
                    "Your clothes dyed black in 24 hours" (literally, "mourning in 24 hours"). This and the previous sign are examples of "catachresis," the application
                    of a term to something it does not properly denote. According to MacMillan (26-27), in the Paris of 1919 "almost every other woman wore mourning."
                </note>
                <note n="150." xml:id="briggs.58" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.150">
                    "Gentlemen-and-ladies," written thus to reflect its pronunciation on the street by waiters, etc. (see lines 157, 191-192). 
                </note>
                <note n="151-55." xml:id="briggs.59" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.151, l.155)">
                    A Roman temple to Mercury, the winged messenger of the gods, once stood on Montmartre, where the cathedral of the Sacré Coeur had recently
                    been completed (dedicated October 1919). <hi rendition="#italic">Templum</hi> is Latin for a sacred space, but "Little temples" might refer to the
                    circular kiosks on the boulevards or even open-air urinals ("<hi rendition="#italic">pissoirs</hi>").
                </note>
                <note n="154-55." xml:id="briggs.60" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.154, l.155)">
                    Harpagon is <hi rendition="#italic">The Miser</hi> of Molière's play (1668), who regards his money as his blood (see V.iii). East of the 
                    Sacré Coeur (sacred heart) is the rue de la Goutte d'Or (golden drop), its name derived from the wealth of vineyards formerly on that site, so the
                    "golden drop of Harpagon's blood" (money) may be contrasted with the blood of the Sacred Heart. But if the "golden drop" is urine (as at lines
                    127-28), this might refer to the homosexual activities for which the <hi rendition="#italic">pissoirs</hi> had been notorious since the eighteenth
                    century. 
                </note>
                <note n="156-57." xml:id="briggs.61" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.156, l.157)">
                    In a typical bar-tabac: vermouth is a type of aperitif; bocks are glasses of beer.
                </note>
                <note n="159-61." xml:id="briggs.62" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.159, l.161)">
                    "Don't close the door, please, the Primus [a compressed air device] will take are of it."
                </note>
                <note n="162." xml:id="briggs.63" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.162">
                    ouvriers: workmen, who discuss recent news items.
                </note>
                <note n="163." xml:id="briggs.64" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.163">
                    "the eight-hour day," demanded by the workers and voted on by the government on April 17 and 23, but the difficulties of implementing it resulted
                    in a general strike on May 1 (lines 235-59, 263; NP13; Hausser 723, 724).
                </note>
                <note n="165." xml:id="briggs.65" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.165">
                    Henri Landru, a serial killer. The police investigated his activities from April to May 1919.
                </note>
                <note n="166." xml:id="briggs.66" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.166">
                    According to a programme for May 2, 1919, the learned seal was "Bichette" and her trainer was Capitaine Juge; the Nouveau Cirque was at 251, rue
                    Saint-Honoré.
                </note>
                <note n="167." xml:id="briggs.67" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.167">
                    On February 19, the anarchist Emile Cottin attempted to assassinate Clemençeau, chairman of the Peace Conference (see notes on lines 35-39, 116-21;
                    Hausser 715; MacMillan 150-151). Cottin was condemned to death in March, but reprieved. His names suggests that of Abbé Charles Cotin (1604-82), habitué
                    of the Hôtel Rambouillet (see <hi rendition="#italic">Madeleine</hi>, 55). 
                </note>
                <note n="169-72." xml:id="briggs.68" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.169, l.172)">
                    Four adjectives probably refer to the previous discussion: "<hi rendition="#italic">méticuleux</hi>," punctilious, scrupulous (Cottin?); 
                    "<hi rendition="#italic">bélligerents</hi>," aggressive, warlike (the Germans, according to the newspapers?); "<hi rendition="#italic">hebdomadaire</hi>,"
                    weekly (of the eight-hour day); "<hi rendition="#italic">immonde</hi>," monstrous, foul (Landru?).
                </note>
                <note n="173-76." xml:id="briggs.69" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.173, l.176)">
                    The Roman Legions in their winged helmets could be seen as invaders of Gaul (France) (like the defeated Germans) or else as France's departing allies.
                </note>
                <note n="177-80." xml:id="briggs.70" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.177, l.180)">
                    Père Lachaise, third of the trio of seventeenth-century clerics, was the Jesuit confessor of Louis XIV and gave his name to Paris's most famous
                    cemetery. He appears wearing a curtain (introducing the theater of war), embroidered with the letter H (pronounced "ash" in French, and so suggesting the
                    words of the English funeral service, "Dust to dust, and ashes to ashes"——in French, <hi rendition="#italic">hache</hi> also means axe. 
                </note>
                <note n="183." xml:id="briggs.71" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.183">
                    Henri Rousseau (1844-1910), known as the Douanier (customs officer) was a French "Sunday" painter whose paintings ("beautiful and horrible") were
                    admired by the avant-garde, especially after Picasso gave a famous dinner for him (1908). HM may have known his painting "La Guerre" (1894).
                </note>
                <note n="184-85." xml:id="briggs.72" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.184, l.185)">
                    The artistic representation of violent events now dominates the poem. WWI failed conspicuously to conform to any rules, let alone the unities
                    of time, place, and action required of classical tragedy; it was closer to Grand Guignol (line 131), which left "The stage . . . thick with corpses."
                </note>
                <note n="186." xml:id="briggs.73" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.186">
                    <hi rendition="#italic">"gaillards,"</hi> big, strapping fellows.
                </note>
                <note n="187." xml:id="briggs.74" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.187">
                    <hi rendition="#italic">"eidola,"</hi> (Greek) ghosts, spirits, images.
                </note>
                <note n="189." xml:id="briggs.75" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.189">
                    Killed in action (literally, "dead on the field of honour").
                </note>
                <note n="191-92." xml:id="briggs.76" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.191, l.192)">
                    "The poor man!"
                </note>
                <note n="193." xml:id="briggs.77" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.193">
                    "petites bourgeoises," middle-class women, collecting money for war victims (149, 157). Picardie is a province in northern France, site of much
                    of the fighting in WWI.
                </note>
                <note n="197." xml:id="briggs.78" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.197">
                    ghoul-like, ghouls rob graves and eat corpses.
                </note>
                <note n="199-200." xml:id="briggs.79" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.199, l.200)">
                    The battle of the Marne (1914) was the worst battle of WWI for the French in terms of losses, their army being almost cut off by German forces
                    in eastern France. The river Marne flows westwards to join the Seine near Paris, where its banks were lined with "guingettes," dance halls, popular at
                    weekends.
                </note>
                <note n="201." xml:id="briggs.80" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.201">
                    "The Grand[s] Boulevards," a series of wide streets, running north of the rue Saint-Honoré, on an east-west axis, lined with theaters and cinemas——
                    a favourite Sunday afternoon walk (the poem seems to zig-zag east from Concorde to the Louvre, west along the rue Saint-Honoré towards the Madeleine, 
                    then east along the Grands Boulevards). From here to line 234 is a description of the Grands Boulevards (NP11).
                </note>
                <note n="203-206." xml:id="briggs.81" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.203, l.206)">
                    "Cloacæ" (Latin), sewers below the boulevards; "Hot indiarubber," from car tires——by 1914, there were 25,000 cars in Paris (Higonnet 187);
                    "Poudre de riz," face powder; "Algerian tobacco" (see line 434) was cheap——themes of empire and racial alterity re-appear, picking up on "Zig-Zag" (line
                    3), cigarette papers rolled around Algerian tobacco and joints.
                </note>
                <note n="207-8." xml:id="briggs.82" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.207, l.208)">
                    "Monsieur Jordain," <hi rendition="#italic">Le Bourgeois Gentilhomme</hi> of Molière's play (1670), dresses up and joins in a Turkish dance in order
                    to become a "Mamamouchi." He is here pictured in the blue and red uniform of the French Algerian army, the Zouaves. "[P]remier danseur," chief soloist;
                    "Ballet Turque [turc]," Turkish ballet.
                </note>
                <note n="209." xml:id="briggs.83" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.209">
                    "Dat's good!" the slogan advertising the breakfast food, "Banania," on a famous poster showing a Senegalese rifleman sitting under a palm tree.
                </note>
                <note n="211." xml:id="briggs.84" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.211">
                    "YANKEES," Americans, either in Paris for the Peace Conference, or staying on after WWI. African Americans often settled in Montmartre, where they
                    found a tolerant atmosphere (Higonnet 340-42). "[A]nd say beesides . . . ": Shakespeare's Moor of Venice, Othello, just before his suicide, remembers how
                    he summarily executed a Turk who had "Beat a Venetian, and traduced the state" (V. ii. 354——thus picking up the Turkish theme).
                </note>
                <note n="212-213." xml:id="briggs.85" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.212, l.213)">
                    <hi rendition="#italic">"Mardi gras,"</hi> Shrove Tuesday, the last day before Lent, the period of forty days fasting before Easter;
                    <hi rendition="#italic">Carême Prenant</hi>," Shrovetide, the days before the start of Lent, a period of merry-making or "Carnival" before the fast;
                    here linked with the Peace Conference, as a celebration before repentance and deprivation.
                </note>
                <note n="214-16." xml:id="briggs.86" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.214, l.216)">
                    Crépes (Shrovetide pancakes) become "crape" thin black mourning veils; "<hi rendition="#italic">Cho-co-lat</hi>," Cho-co-late——the second "o" is long,
                    and emphasised in French pronunciation.
                </note>
                <note n="217." xml:id="briggs.87" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.217">
                    "The women rock themselves backwards and forwards on their haunches."
                </note>
                <note n="219." xml:id="briggs.88" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.219">
                    Square-cut beards, as portrayed on Assyrian statues.
                </note>
                <note n="221." xml:id="briggs.89" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.221">
                    Tart: sharp, acid; "The tart little race" might be the Armenians, victims of Turkish massacres, who sent a special delegation to the Peace Conference
                    (MacMillan 377).
                </note>
                <note n="223-24." xml:id="briggs.90" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.223, l.224)">
                    "Yesyesyes, isn't it exciting——and such good value for money. Cheese isn't a rational dish" (see line 37).
                </note>
                <note n="225-227." xml:id="briggs.91" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.225, l.227)">
                    "A-a-ah yes, he's a charming boy. / I think every honest woman must recognize herself in Anna Karenina." Tolstoy's novel <hi rendition="#italic">Anna 
                    Karenina</hi> (1877) is the story of a woman who abandons marriage and child for her lover (see line 282). 
                </note>
                <note n="228." xml:id="briggs.92" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.228">
                    "catalepsy," a seizure or tance in which consciousness is suspended (for other tranced moments, see lines 20, 320). French café gossip is contrasted with
                    the silence of Germans. 
                </note>
                <note n="229-34." xml:id="briggs.93" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.229, l.234)">
                    Subaqueous: (constructed) under water; this passage echoes the preface to <hi rendition="#italic">Madeleine</hi>, where "Life" (or as here, "Experience")
                    is the material out of which Art is gradually formed.
                </note>
                <note n="236-37." xml:id="briggs.94" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.236, l.237)">
                    With these lines, the description of the Grands Boulevards comes to an end (NP11), suggesting, perhaps, that the life on the boulevards provides raw
                    material needing to be formed into speech or words, if it is to become art ("coming to" could mean coming back to consciousness). Lines 232-34 themselves burst
                    into "vastness" after the six narrow lines that precede them (see also Tennyson's poem, "Vastness").
                </note>
                <note n="238-363." xml:id="briggs.95" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.238, l.262)">
                    May I is celebrated as Labor Day in France, but in 1919 there was a general strike in Paris, with violent clashes between the authorities and the workers,
                    some of whom marched with knives between their teeth (Hausser 726; MacMillan 273). The vertical lettering emphasizes the disruption of normal order, representing
                    the lines of marchers, and possibly the stems of the (absent) lily of the valley, usually sold on  May I, to give to friends or sweethearts as a bringer of luck
                    (106, NP13).
                </note>
                <note n="263-65." xml:id="briggs.96" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.263, l.265)">
                    The struggle between the chaos of life and the structure of art (226-32) now becomes a "ritual fight" between two virgins, as the year progresses from
                    "The wicked April moon" (<hi rendition="#italic">la lune rousse</hi>) to the month of May, sacred to the Virgin Mary. The April moon is the lunar month after
                    Easter, characterized by cold, harsh winds that seem to scorch (<hi rendition="#italic">roussir</hi>) the new growth (NP14). "[H]er sweet body" could be that
                    of Paris.
                </note>
                <note n="266." xml:id="briggs.97" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.266">
                    Punning on the English expression, "the silence of the grave," <hi rendition="#italic">la grève</hi> is the strike (on May 1), with a further underlying
                    wordplay; since <hi rendition="#italic">la grève</hi> means the river bank——the place de <hi rendition="#italic">Grève</hi> (now, place de l'Hôtel de Ville)
                    being where Parisian workers assembled to "<hi rendition="#italic">faire la grève</hi>," or go on strike.
                </note>
                <note n="271." xml:id="briggs.98" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.271">
                    "the mysterious island gardens" seem to be those of the Carrousel, running from the Arc de Triomphe du Carrousel down to the Tuileries.
                </note>
                <note n="272-274." xml:id="briggs.99" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.272, l.274)">
                    The Seine winds eastward through the center of Paris, reaching the sea at Le Havre. "Ruminating," literally, chewing the cud, and thus recycling
                    or recirculating, also suggests the river's passage through the fertile dairy-farming province of Normandy. Initially associated with the underworld (line 10),
                    the Seine is here (and later, line 414) associated with the Freudian unconscious, which increasingly asserts itself as dreams (271, and see lines 310, 376), 
                    anticipated by the melting of the Louvre (265; compare 311-15).
                </note>
                <note n="275." xml:id="briggs.100" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.275">
                    "King-fishers," small, bright blue diving birds.
                </note>
                <note n="277-78." xml:id="briggs.101" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.277, l.278)">
                    Paris now becomes a sequence of pictures: the "two-dimensional" (as at line 403) silhouette of the Eiffel Tower (a favorite subject for artists)
                    is "etched" (engraved, black on white), while the soldiers encamped in the Tuileries are drawn in colored chalk, and the page ends with (imaginary)
                    oil paintings.
                </note>
                <note n="279-83." xml:id="briggs.102" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.279, l.283)">
                    "The <hi rendition="#italic">Poilus</hi>" (literally "hairy"), French WWI soldiers in blue uniforms, with "<hi rendition="#italic">Tierre 
                    de Sienne</hi>" (burnt Sienna, reddish brown) packs, around the "gray sphinx" look like the chalk sketches, "edited" (i.e. published) in the rue
                    des Pyramides, a street where souvenirs are sold. The combination of sphinx and pyramids recalls Napoleon's campaign in Egypt, as well as WWI operations
                    in Egypt (MacMillan 382-83, 401). 
                </note>
                <note n="284-89." xml:id="briggs.103" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.284, l.289)">
                    "Désœvrement" (idleness, lack of occupation, suffered by demobilized soldiers) suggests Vronsky; "Apprehension" suggests Anna, the lovers at
                    the center of Tolstoy's <hi rendition="#italic">Anna Karenina</hi> (line 224). In part 4, they wake from similar dreams of a sinister Russian peasant
                    (a "mujik"), perhaps unconsciously anticipating the Bolshevik Revoltuion (1917). 
                </note>
                <note n="290-93." xml:id="briggs.104" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.290, l.293)">
                    Even the most violent and calamitous moments of history can be transformed into the tranquility of art. Clio, the Greek muse of history, becomes
                    a French painter, stilling the watery flux of life. Shadrach et al. were cast by Nebuchadnezzar into the fiery furnace (<hi rendition="#italic">Daniel</hi>
                    3.12-30), but in art they become "motionless and plastic."
                </note>
                <note n="295-98." xml:id="briggs.105" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.295, l.298)">
                    Manet's <hi rendition="#italic">Massacres</hi> . . ." a series of paintings imagined as hanging in the Louvre, depicting violent moments of French
                    history: Manet (1832-83) is imagined portraying the massacres of "les journées de Juin" (days of June, 1848 when protesters were rounded up, disarmed, and
                    killed by the army); David (1748-1825), as painting the taking of the Bastille (July 14, 1789, the beginning of the French Revolution); Nicolas Poussin
                    (1594-1665), as depicting the uprisings of the Fronde (1649, 1652) (see <hi rendition="#italic">Madeleine</hi>, 11-12). Pages 13-15 survive in a proof,
                    corrected by HM. Here the first imaginary painting was originally "Cézanne's <hi rendition="#italic">Quatorze Juillet</hi>"——apparently altered because its
                    subject, "14 July," was too close to David's. "Manet's <hi rendition="#italic">Massacres des Jours de Juin</hi>" was substituted. Manet actually painted
                    the "Execution of Maximilian" (1867) and the executions of May 1871. HM's revisions produce a historical sequence, running from the strike of May 1, 1919,
                    back through the risings of 1848, 1789, and 1652, to illustrate French political resistance.
                </note>
                <note n="299-301." xml:id="briggs.106" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.299, l.301)">
                    Like Clio (but not like Vronsky), the Virgin has been busy——creating business for (and later actually window-dressing) Paris's three largest and
                    best-known department stores——les Galéries Lafayette, le Bon Marche (see line 95), and la Samaritaine. [The last two lines of this page and the first twelve
                    of the next were cut from the 1973 edition].
                </note>
                <note n="300-302." xml:id="briggs.106.1" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.300, l.302)">
                    According to HM's notes (NP14), during Lent, department store windows displayed wax models dressed for First Communion in white veils and ties (knots
                    of ribbon) as "bait," to encourage young girls to participate by showing the pretty clothes they could wear. But these "Waxen Pandoras" are also "bait" in a
                    further sense, since (according to Hesiod, lines 80-82) Pandora was sent by Zeus to tempt Prometheus and punish him for stealing fire from the gods. Pandora
                    was modeled from clay (not wax), and carried a jar containing all the evils of the world. When she opened it, they all flew out into the world, except Hope
                    (HM's own name), left inside the jar.
                </note>
                <note n="305." xml:id="briggs.107" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.305">
                    <hi rendition="#italic">"Catéchisme de Persévérence,"</hi>  a popular nineteenth-century Catholic manual by Jean-Joseph Gaume. The decrees of the "Seven
                    Œcumenical Councils" (Nicea I, 324 A.D.-Nicea II, 787 A.D.) embody the central doctrines of Christianity; "format" means "size"; 
                    "<hi rendition="#italic">Bibliotheque Rose</hi>," a series of books for girls published by Hachette.
                </note>
                <note n="308-9." xml:id="briggs.108" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.308, l.309)">
                    "First Communion." Prometheus has swallowed the "bait" of Pandora, or the communion wafer, or is excited by the First Communicants.
                </note>
                <note n="310-12." xml:id="briggs.109" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.310, l.312)">
                    "Petits Lycéens," little high-school children. "Por-no-gra-phie," spelled out as if for children, is a Greek word meaning, literally, writings
                    about prostitution; "pigmy brides" are miniature brides of Christ. "Pigmy" is a Greek word for the forearm or fist, anticipating the cannibal imagery
                    that follows. ("teknophagiai," the eating of children, is discussed by JH in <hi rendition="#italic">Themis</hi> 248-49).
                </note>
                <note n="313-14." xml:id="briggs.110" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.313, l.314)">
                    "Little St. Hugh" (not an actual saint), according to anti-Semitic legend, a child murdered by Jews in Lincoln (1255). Chaucer's 
                    <hi rendition="#italic">Prioress's Tale</hi> tells a similar story. By eating the body of Christ (the Jew) at first communion, the children
                    "avenge" St. Hugh's murder.
                </note>
                <note n="315." xml:id="briggs.111" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.315">
                    A photographic studio in Paris? A peepshow?
                </note>
                <note n="319." xml:id="briggs.112" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.319">
                    Périgord is a rural region in south-western France, part of hte poem's tour of provinces.
                </note>
                <note n="320-23." xml:id="briggs.113" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.320, l.323)">
                    The Louvre is the great Palace at the heart of Paris, now an art gallery; the Ritz is a Hotel at 15, Place Vendôme; the Palais-Royal[e] is opposite
                    the Louvre; the Hôtel de Ville, the Paris Mairie (or town hall), is east of the Louvre on the rue de Rivoli. All are solid, indeed massive buildings, that
                    could only appear "light and frail" in a rising atmosphere of dreams (see line 265).
                </note>
                <note n="324-25." xml:id="briggs.114" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.324, l.325)">
                    "junketing," feasting, merrymaking. Masks and dominoes are carnival disguises (the domino is the cloak to go with the mask), typically worn by the
                    aristocracy, but here by "citizens," thus anticipating the Revolution.
                </note>
                <note n="326." xml:id="briggs.115" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.326">
                    "On the occasion of the marriage of Monsieur le Dauphin," the marriage celebrations of the future Louis XVI to Marie-Antoinette. In the course of these
                    (May 30-31, 1770), a display of fireworks created a stampede in which several hundred people were crushed to death or pushed into the river.
                </note>
                <note n="327-29." xml:id="briggs.116" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.327, l.329)">
                    The Hôtel de l'Elysée, 3, rue de Beaune, where HM stayed in Paris and apparently wrote this poem, was a hotel in the modern sense, as well as in
                    the older sense of a grand town house, formerly the property of Mme du Deffand, famous for her <hi rendition="#italic">salon</hi>. "Tranced" (line 20, and
                    perhaps 45), trance states, and the automatic writing they generated was to fascinate the surrealists. It is possible that the whole poem, flickering
                    between "real" and imagined Paris sights, was generated by this "tranced" moment of gazing out of the window (Keatsian "magic casements, opening on the
                    foam / Of perilous seas, in fairy lands forlorn"?)
                </note>
                <note n="330." xml:id="briggs.117" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.330">
                    "Hawkers...liturgically," street peddlars...in the style of a church service.
                </note>
                <note n="332-33." xml:id="briggs.118" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.332, l.333)">
                    "Triptolemos," a legendary king of Eleusis who founded the Mysteries and taught men agriculture (including how to make bread). As a baby (wrapped
                    in swaddling clothes that make him "loaf-shaped"), he was loved by Demeter (Ceres), probably identified with the "women in black shawls."
                </note>
                <note n="333-34." xml:id="briggs.119" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.333, l.334)">
                    "Workmen in pale blue," wore denim overalls; "Barrows" belong to street vendors displaying their wares.
                </note>
                <note n="340." xml:id="briggs.120" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.340">
                    Ovid, roman poet and storyteller (43 B.C.-17 A.D.), exiled to Tomis on the Black Sea, but not a "thrall" (i.e., slave) in Fairyland (as was the narrator
                    of Keats's poem, "La Belle Dame Sans Merci"). The resulting "lost romance" is imagined as having inspired Italian painters, as their "guild-secret," peculiar
                    to their craft. 
                </note>
                <note n="347-48." xml:id="briggs.121" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.347, l.348)">
                    Three landmarks of seventeenth-century Paris to the north and east, by 1919 in a state of disrepair, and thus "exquisitely dying" (see line 41).
                </note>
                <note n="350." xml:id="briggs.122" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.350, l.350.graphic)">
                    Quiet was expected for the dying. The eight bars of music are marked "dim——in——u-end-do" (growing softer) to "ppp," pianissimo, very quiet indeed.
                    The melancholy aria is "Lascia ch'io pianga," from Handel's opera <hi rendition="#italic">Rinaldo</hi> (1711), "Let me weep for my cruel fate, and let me sigh
                    for my liberty" (recalling Ovid's misery in exile?).
                </note>
                <note n="351-52." xml:id="briggs.123" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.351, l.352)">
                    The beautiful church of Saint Thomas d'Aquin (begun 1688, completed 1766) stands near the end of the rue de Beaune. L'impasse des Deux Anges (the
                    mews of the two angels), is close by. The angels may be linked with Jacob (see <hi rendition="#italic">Genesis</hi> 28.12, or 32.24-29), though "two angels"
                    are particularly connected with Lot and the destruction of the cities of the plain (<hi rendition="#italic">Genesis</hi> 19.1-17), punished by God for
                    homosexuality (see Cocteau, 28-29, 47; 45, 66). The name of the "impasse" may also suggest lesbianism. It was close to Natalie Barney's house (at 20, rue
                    Jacob) and is referred to in Djuna Barnes's <hi rendition="#italic">The Ladies' Almanack</hi>.
                </note>
                <note n="353-54." xml:id="briggs.124" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.353, l.354)">
                    "Impasse," a blind alley, also suggests "deadlock" (both in French and English), and "impassive" (i.e., blank or inexpressive, 
                    <hi rendition="#italic">impassible</hi>). The French expression for walls without windows, <hi rendition="#italic">murs aveugles</hi> (blind walls) may
                    have suggested the comparison with blind dogs. The ghosts, watched by the "impassive windows" (compare line 108), introduce a pageant of the city's
                    famous dead.
                </note>
                <note n="358." xml:id="briggs.125" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.358">
                    Sebastopol, port on the Black sea, besieged and eventually captured (1856), by English and French troops (greatly aided by Algerians, the "Zouaves")
                    during the Crimean War, and commemorated by a street name and a metro station. [HM altered the nun's "Masses" to "dirges" in the 1973 edition.]
                </note>
                <note n="359-66." xml:id="briggs.126" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.359, l.366)">
                    The memorial plaque for the playwright (1622-73) on his house at 40, rue de Richelieu, on the Right Bank, north of the Louvre (see lines 153, 204).
                    "The dying seventeenth century" is followed by the memorial plaque for the Enlightenment philosopher Voltaire (1694-1778), who died at no.1, rue de Beaune,
                    next to or even part of HM's hotel.
                </note>
                <note n="367-70." xml:id="briggs.127" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.367, l.370)">
                    Chateaubriand, Romantic poet and memoirist (1768-1848), died close by, at 118-120 rue du Bac, with the blind Mme Récamier at his bedside (lines
                    64-65). These writers typify three different centuries, and three different French styles.
                </note>
                <note n="372-74." xml:id="briggs.128" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.372, l.374)">
                    "Paradise" is almost an anagram of "Paris" and "dies." Les Champs Elysées, Paris's most famous avenue, means "the Elysian fields," in classical 
                    literature, the home of the dead.
                </note>
                <note n="375-76." xml:id="briggs.129" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.375, l.376)">
                    The French critic Charles Sainte-Beuve (1804-69) was the friend and rival of the poet and novelist Victor Hugo (1802-85), and the lover of his wife
                    Adèle. The Pont Neuf ("New Bridge," now the oldest, completed 1604) would take Saint-Beuve from his house on the Left Bank to the Right (where the Hugos
                    lived, at 6 place des Vosges).
                </note>
                <note n="377-80." xml:id="briggs.130" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.377, l.380)">
                    The duc de la Rochefoucauld (1613-80), author of <hi rendition="#italic">Maximes</hi> (1664) and a close friend of Mme de Lafayette (1634-93), 
                    author of <hi rendition="#italic">La Princesse de Clèves</hi> (1678). He passes Saint-Beuve on the Pont Neuf as he crosses to the Left Bank to visit Mme 
                    Lafayette in the rue Ferou. They cannot see each other, perhaps because of the centuries between them, but the duc had figured in Saint-Beuve's great study
                    of the seventeenth century, <hi rendition="#italic">Port-Royal</hi> (1840-59). The "<hi rendition="#italic">salon d'automne</hi>" exhibited avant-garde 
                    painting; it was originally formed by a group of fauvists and postimpressionists in 1903 (Shattuck 61). 
                </note>
                <note n="382." xml:id="briggs.131" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.382">
                    "It's close, sultry" (literally, heavy, as in "Heavy sweet going," line 311). 
                </note>
                <note n="384." xml:id="briggs.132" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.384">
                    "Benediction," a Catholic service. "Notre-Dame-des-Champs" (Our-Lady-of-the-fields), one of the oldest churches in Paris; formerly standing in fields on
                    Montparnasse, was rebuilt in 1876. Its metro station is south of rue du Bac on the Nord-Sud line, between Port-Royal (line 439) and the garden of the nuns of
                    St. Vincent de Paul, on the rue de Babylone (now the Jardin Catherine Laboure).
                </note>
                <note n="386-89." xml:id="briggs.133" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.386, l.389)">
                    The Virgin wears the elaborately starched headdress of the nuns of St. Vincent de Paul (winged like the Roman helmets of line 172) and probably sits
                    in their convent garden (see above), where the west wall would have been covered with plum and apricot trees, and there are still box hedges. The Holy Ghost
                    descended as a dove, and "cooing" and "(dove)-cots" are common to babies and doves (compare Cocteau 22: "Dieu roucoule au sommet des arbres"). 
                </note>
                <note n="390." xml:id="briggs.134" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.390">
                    "The Seven Stages," possibly half of the fourteen Stations of the Cross, performed on Good Friday, representing Christ's final sufferings; "cut in box"
                    either means carved in boxwood, or from topiary (pruning box hedges into shapes). Churches display branches of box during Easter week. [The last five lines
                    of this page and the first six lines of the next were omitted from the 1973 edition.]
                </note>
                <note n="391-93." xml:id="briggs.135" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.391, l.393)">
                    White ("Madonna") lilies, the Virgin's flower. Votive offerings result from a religious promise. The Jap(anese) convert is the painter L. T. Foujita
                    (1886-1968), who painted pictures of the Virgin and Child in soft colors (1917-18), often in shapes resembling bulbs. 
                </note>
                <note n="394-95." xml:id="briggs.136" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.394, l.395)">
                    "troubadour," Provencal wandering minstrel. The cult of courtly love voiced in troubadour poetry was linked with the cult of the Virgin; "her," i.e.,
                    to her. "Venial sins" are lesser than Deadly Sins (at lines 120, 426-27).
                </note>
                <note n="397-98." xml:id="briggs.137" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.397, l.398)">
                    The garden wall becomes the evening sky, hung with the plums of Paradise, where wasps never fret (eat away) the fruit; on the Solférino bridge, 
                    however, people look like flies, nibbling into the apricot (colored) sky (lines 399-401).
                </note>
                <note n="399-400." xml:id="briggs.138" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.399, l.400) #l.403"><!--CHECK...add #403-->
                    "Freedom!" "The Press!" names of evening newspapers shouted by street vendors. 
                </note>
                <note n="401-2." xml:id="briggs.139" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.401, l.402)">
                    "Petit-Palais," built for the 1900 World Exhibition, west of the Place de Concorde, and perhaps just visible from a high west-facing window at
                    the end of the rue de Beaune. At susnset in the Algerian desert the "muezzin" gives the Muslim call to prayer.
                </note>
                <note n="407-12." xml:id="briggs.140" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.407, l.412)">
                    "Fiacres," light horse-drawn four-wheeled cabs. Looking west-ward, HM might just have seen figures on the old Pont Solférino (demolished 1961),
                    silhouetted like flies against the celestial (heavenly) evening haze; "tippetted pelisse," a fur-collared cloak. Louis-Philippe, "the citizen king," reigned
                    1830-48, when portraits in silhouette, cut from black paper, were in vogue. 
                </note>
                <note n="413-14." xml:id="briggs.141" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.413, l.414)">
                    The Quais are the streets along the banks of the Seine, where the "bouquinistes" (box-owners, booksellers) sell their wares from green boxes, which they
                    lock up at night.
                </note>
                <note n="415." xml:id="briggs.142" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.415">
                    Paris has twenty <hi rendition="#italic">arrondissements</hi> (administrative districts). The VIIme lies immediately south of the river, on the Left Bank,
                    and includes the rue de Beaune, like the neighboring VIme, this was an up-market address, known as the "Faubourg Saint-Germain."
                </note>
                <note n="418." xml:id="briggs.143" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.418">
                    "Hyperbórean," northern. The poem prepares to move up to Montmartre, in the north of Paris. 
                </note>
                <note n="421." xml:id="briggs.144" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.421">
                    "Ramparts," mounds built for defense. The Louvre was initially built as a fortress (in 1200). Here ramparts keep the river, and perhaps the unconscious,
                    at bay.
                </note>
                <note n="422-23." xml:id="briggs.145" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.422, l.423)">
                    Sigmund Freud (1856-1939), Viennese theorist of sexuality and the unconscious, dredges the river, associated with rising dreams (lines 269-72). The
                    combination of Freud and electricity evokes modern life. Paris had had electrically lit advertisements from 1912 (Higonnet 145, 358, and compare "Contrastes":
                    "Il pleut les globes electriques," Cendrars 71).
                </note>
                <note n="424-26." xml:id="briggs.146" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.424, l.426)">
                    Taxis line up on the page, as they do on the streets.
                </note>
                <note n="429." xml:id="briggs.147" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.429">
                    "their meat," perhaps their clients (see line 4; the opening themes are now replayed). 
                </note>
                <note n="430." xml:id="briggs.148" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.430">
                    "padre," "Father" (a Catholic priest) strikes at the Moulin Rouge (literally, the Red Windmill), Paris's most famous cabaret show (on the Place Blanche,
                    Montmartre). To tilt with windmills is to make an ineffectual attack (from <hi rendition="#italic">Don Quixote</hi>).
                </note>
                <note n="431." xml:id="briggs.149" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.431">
                    Black music notes become African American musicians playing jazz; "syncopation," shifting of the regular musical beat, as in jazz. Today this sentence is
                    disturbingly racist, although the black musicians, like the lesbians in the following lines, introduce a liberating discourse of racial and sexual alterity.
                    Jazz was brought to Paris by black U.S. army bands at the end of World War I, and was fashionable in Montmartre (Higonnet 341).
                </note>
                <note n="433." xml:id="briggs.150" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.433"> <!--CHECK...add #438 ....made change and deleted second target l.438-->
                    Literally, all the cards (or maps) work with, walk with or go out with a match, but the exact meaning is hard to decide. It might refer to packs
                    of cards given out in cafés, with boxes of matches, but "cartes" was also slang for prostitutes, and an "allumette" might be a sexual tease, or even a penis.
                    A song refrain?
                </note>
                <note n="434." xml:id="briggs.151" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.434">
                    Fifty pairs of glasses, designed to correct American "astigmatism" (a sight defect that prevents focusing), reflect a (leg) show, saucily entitled
                    "the Masque of the Seven Deadly Sins" (see line 120), a pseudo-religious title for a secular event, perhaps suggesting a further clash between the Virgin
                    and "The wicked April moon."
                </note>
                <note n="424-26." xml:id="briggs.152" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.436, l.438)">
                    Stage performers, like courtesans, were often supposed lesbian, and lesbianism was fashionable in Paris at this time (Higonnet 112-13). The spelling
                    "gurls" may indicate an American accent, but "girls" was also French slang for both lesbians and chorus girls. 
                </note>
                <note n="439." xml:id="briggs.153" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.439">
                    Dawn brings the poem's time scheme of a single day to a close. 
                </note>
                <note n="440." xml:id="briggs.154" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.440">
                    Paul Verlaine (1844-96), lyric poet and decadent, fell in love with the precocious poet Arthur Rimbaud (1854-91), author of "L'Alchimie du verbe" (a
                    section of his prose poem, <hi rendition="#italic">Une Saison en Enfer</hi>). "Alchemy," the transformation of base metals into gold, is also a figure
                    for the coming of dawn. "absynthe" [unusually spelled with a "y"] is a powerful green spirit distilled from wormwood to which Verlaine was addicted.
                    Picasso's 1903 painting, "Portrait du poète Cornuti, ou l'Absinthe" is a form of homage to Verlaine. Algerian tobacco was used to roll cheap cigarettes
                    and joints (lines 3, 203). 
                </note>
                <note n="445-46." xml:id="briggs.155" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.445, l.446)">
                    Raymond Poincaré was president of France (1913-20). The poem here rocks between homosexuality and heterosexuality (the marriage bed, birth), 
                    between couples and single lives. 
                </note>
                <note n="447." xml:id="briggs.156" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.447">
                    "Port-Royal," maternity hospital on the Left Bank, formerly a convent associated with Jansenism (NP15), a movement within the French seventeenth
                    century church persecuted by the authorities (and the focus of Saint-Beuve's study, <hi rendition="#italic">Port-Royal</hi>). In chapter XVI of
                    <hi rendition="#italic">Madeleine</hi>, Madeleine visits the Abbaye, whose mistress, Mère Agnès Arnauld, is a portrait of JH (157). 
                </note>
                <note n="448-49." xml:id="briggs.157" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.448, l.449)">
                    This line suggests Duncan Grant's painting "Le Crime et le Châtiment" (ca. 1909), especially since Dostoevsky's novel (1866) was usually translated
                    "<hi rendition="#italic">Crime et Chàtiment</hi>." HM knew Grant, and may have known that the painting showed Marjorie Strachey reading that novel. 
                </note>
                <note n="451." xml:id="briggs.158" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.451">
                    "Les Halles," until the late 1960s, Paris's main food market, rebuilt of wrought iron and glass (1866). 
                </note>
                <note n="454." xml:id="briggs.159" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.454">
                    "I salute you Paris full of grace," echoing the Catholic prayer, "Ave Maria," "Je vous salue Marie pleine de grace" (see Dedication; Cocteau 82: "Je
                    vous salue pleine de grace...o sainte mère").
                </note>
                <note n="455-59." xml:id="briggs.160" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#range(l.455, l.459)">
                    The poem ends with the constellation of Ursa Major, the great she-bear, part of the private code between HM and JH, who sometimes signed off letters
                    to HM with this star-sign in reverse.
                </note>
                <note n="462." xml:id="briggs.161" resp="Briggs" anchored="true" target="#l.462">
                    [1916, the "6" overwritten as "9"] 
                    On the final page, HM makes a further highly original gesture by providing a set of notes to her admittedly difficult poem. Though not without precedent
                    (Pope had annotated his "Dunciad"), it was unusual for an author to annotate her own text thus. Brief and fragmentary though her notes are, they offer a
                    fresh perspective on the poem, and incidentally anticipate T. S. Eliot's use of notes in <hi rendition="#italic">The Waste Land</hi> (1922). 
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>    
</TEI>
